Academic Planning Office fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Academic Planning Office fonds
1961 - 1972
F-49
25 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Academic Planning Office
The position of Director of Academic Planning (also referred to as the Academic Planner) was created by President McTaggart-Cowan in 1963 in order to help plan, organize, and formulate policies on the academic activities of the University. Duties of the director included providing assistance to the President, the Senate, and the Board of Governors in making decisions as to the format of the academic year to be adopted by SFU (e.g., a semester system versus a term year system); the organization of University faculties (including making decisions as to which faculties were to be included in the University); the planning of University academic priorities in relation to programs offered by other universities in the community; the setting of admissions policies; the establishment of student study formats (such as sizes of lectures and tutorials, and grading standards); the formulation of policies regarding academic staff; and the formulation of expansion plans for the University. The Academic Planner reported to the Vice-President, Academic, until the position of Academic Planner was eliminated in 1974.
On November 14, 1963, the University hired its first Director of Academic Planning, Ronald James Baker, who assumed his duties on January 1, 1964. On December 10 of that year he also became the head of SFU's English department. He served in these positions until 1969, when he left SFU to become President of the University of Prince Edward Island. At that time, John Chase took over duties as Academic Planner. Chase left the position in 1974 to become Director of Institutional Studies (now Analytical Studies) for SFU.
published
Full
Revised
Title based on the name of the body.
Fonds consists of records of the Academic Planner for SFU. Fonds includes, correspondence, policies, reference material, and other materials. Materials relate to the formation of University policies, the appointment of University faculty and staff, the dissemination of information regarding SFU through various media outlets, and other functions.
Files within series are arranged chronologically.
Baker, Ron; Chase, John
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
Consult the Ronald J. Baker fonds. Also consult the Analytical Studies (F-52) fonds for additional correspondence of John Chase as Academic Planner.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File lists are available.
- Director's correspondence, 1963 - 1972; F-49-1; 12 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of correspondence of the Director of Academic Planning. Correspondence includes letters received and copies of letters sent. Correspondents include members of the media, university administrators, and potential University employees and students. Materials relate to the formulation of University policies, the dissemination of information regarding the University, the staffing of the University, and other topics.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  Series includes an index to correspondence from 1963 to 1965.
  - Index to correspondence, 1963 - 1965; F-49-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Director's correspondence, 1963; F-49-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1964; F-49-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1964; F-49-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1964; F-49-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1964; F-49-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1965; F-49-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1965; F-49-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1965; F-49-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1965; F-49-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
  - Director's correspondence, 1966 - 1972; F-49-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 49-1)
    Restricted in part
- Policies and reference material, 1961 - 1967; F-49-2; 13 cm of textual records
  Series consists of draft policies for SFU, as well as reference material used to formulate those policies. Policies relate to academic plans, examinations, credit hours and degree requirements, student activity fees, academic calendars, course numbering systems, staffing, academic freedom, admission requirements, and other issues. Reference material consists of reports and other records from other universities regarding their policies, procedures, and circumstances. Series also includes a tabulation of credit hours taught at SFU in the 1967 summer semester.
  - Academic policies, 1964 - 1965; F-49-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - small 49-2)
  - Background papers, vol. 1, 1961 - 1965; F-49-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - small 49-2)
  - Background papers, vol. 2, 1961 - 1965; F-49-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - small 49-2)
  - Background papers, vol. 3, 1961 - 1965; F-49-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - small 49-2)
  - Year round operation, 1964; F-49-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - small 49-2)
  - Semester credit hours taught, 1967-3, F-49-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - small 49-2)